{"tossups": [{"question": "With his assistant, William Alexander, this man took on a 1964 case which ended with a verdict of \"guilty of murder with malice.\" This man prosecuted Jack Ruby, the assassin of Lee Harvey Oswald. In another case, this district attorney for Dallas County was opposed by the representatives of Linda Coffee. This man was a defendant in that case which found the central choice to be \u201cfundamental\u201d and included the establishment of a \u201cright to privacy\u201d standard. For the point, name this anti-abortion activist who was the named defendant in a case brought by Norma McCorvey, also known as \"Jane Roe.\"", "answer": "Henry <b><u>Wade</u></b> (or Henry Menasco <b><u>Wade</u></b>; accept <em>Roe v.</em> <em><b><u>Wade</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Gruesomely, this non-Chinese organization nailed street dogs to lampposts with signs declaiming that Deng Xiaoping [[SHAO-PENG]] was a traitor to the Communist Party for his capitalistic economic reforms. This organization worked in tandem with the Tupac Amaru movement to control countryside communities known as <em>Rondas</em>. Abimael Guzman called for this organization to undertake the \"People's War,\" which included a campaign of terrorism in Lima. For the point, name this guerrilla movement of Peru, a Maoist insurgency eradicated by Alberto Fujimori.", "answer": "<b><u>Shining Path</u></b> (or <b><u>Sendero Luminoso</u></b>; accept <b><u>Communist Party of Peru</u></b> before \"Peru\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A member of this party wrote the draft of the Ku Klux Klan Act while another member referred to bankers as \u201cHuns and Vandals\u201d when accepting the nomination for vice president. Peter Cooper was this party\u2019s first presidential candidate but received less than one percent of the popular vote. The Specie Payment Resumption Act and the Coinage Act of 1873 were opposed by this party, which merged with the Populist Party in the 1890s. Barzillai J. Chambers and Benjamin F. Butler were members of, for the point, what political party that advocated for the circulation of paper money?", "answer": "<b><u>Greenback</u></b> Party (or <b><u>Greenback</u></b> Labor Party; prompt on \"Independent Party\u201d or \"National Independent Party\u201d)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A state ruled from this city was overthrown by the warrior queen Gudit according to legend. A ruler of this city named Kaleb invaded the Kingdom of Himyar on the request of Byzantine Emperor Justin. It\u2019s not Medina, but early Muslims sheltered in this city during the First Hijra. The Zagwe dynasty replaced a family that ruled from this Tigrayan city, whose rulers spoke the Ge\u2019ez [[GEZ]] language. The bishop Frumentius converted a ruler of this city, Ezena, to Christanity. For the point, name this city in northern Ethiopia that was the capital of a namesake empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Axum</u></b> (accept <b><u>Axum</u></b>ite Empire or Kingdom; accept Kingdom or Empire of <b><u>Axum</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One precursor to this event was William Ortiz being put in \u201ckeeplock.\u201d Following this event, the Weather Underground detonated a bomb near Russell Oswald\u2019s office. To investigate this event, the McKay Commission was appointed by Governor Nelson Rockefeller. That commission\u2019s report criticized Rockefeller, the Department of Corrections, and the New York State Police\u2019s handling of this event. Occurring in a namesake western New York prison, for the point, what is this bloodiest prison uprising in American history?", "answer": "<b><u>Attica</u></b> Prison Riot (accept Massacre, Rebellion, or Uprising in place of \"Riot\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this dynasty, a resurgence of Confucianism was led by Cheng Yi and Zhu Xi [[SHE]]. The scroll painting <em>Along the River During the Qingming</em> [[CHING-MING]] <em>Festival</em> was created during this dynasty. This dynasty lost to Zhong Hongfan\u2019s far smaller naval force at the Battle of Yamen. This dynasty\u2019s \u201cSouthern Period\u201d began when the Jurchen Jin Dynasty conquered its capital of Kaifeng. Inventions during this dynasty include the compass and gunpowder. For the point, name this Chinese dynasty that was conquered by the Mongols.", "answer": "<b><u>Song</u></b> dynasty (or <b><u>S\u00f2ng</u></b> ch\u00e1o)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Thrasybulus [[thrass-ih-BYOO-luss]] and his pro-democracy exiles occupied this city in an attempted last stand against the troops of Pausanias, who fought in support of the puppet government known as \"The Thirty Tyrants.\" Cleisthenes [[KLY-stheh-neez]] established this city as a <em>deme</em> [[DEH-meh]] in the 5th century BCE, and this port in Attica is where Plato's <em>Republic</em> begins. The modern iteration of this city is the largest passenger port in Europe, while its ancient counterpart served as the primary port of the Delian League. The Long Walls ran from Athens to, for the point, what nearby port city on the Aegean Sea?", "answer": "<b><u>Piraeus</u></b> (or <b><u>Peirai\u00e1s</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Ed Daly, the president of World Airlines, is credited with developing this operation. Captain Dennis Traynor crash-landed a C-5A Galaxy plane onto a rice field in the beginning stages of this operation. This operation was announced by Gerald Ford during a news conference in San Diego, and he welcomed those rescued at San Francisco International Airport two days later. A non-profit called Operation Reunite was established 30 years after this operation took place. For the point, what 1975 operation involved the evacuation of over 3,000 children from South Vietnam?", "answer": "Operation <b><u>Babylift</u></b> (accept descriptive answers involving the evacuation of <b><u>children</u></b> from <b><u>Vietnam</u></b>; prompt on \"Fall of Saigon\" or \"South Vietnam\"; prompt on \"Evacuation from Saigon\" or \"South Vietnam\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Ernest Arthur Dickinson put down a short-lived rebellion which aimed to restart this conflict led by Abd al-Qadir known as the Wad Habuba Revolt. Garnet Wolseley led a relief force to assist the besieged general \"Chinese\" Gordon during this war's Emin Pasha Expedition. During this war, future Secretary of War Herbert Kitchener implemented the first use of hollow point munitions known as \"Dum Dum\" bullets at the Battle of Omdurman. Sufi religious figure Muhammad Ahmad led, for the point, which late 19th century revolt in Sudan?", "answer": "<b><u>Mahdi</u></b>st War (accept <b><u>Mahdi</u></b>st Revolt; <b><u>Mahdi</u></b> Revolt; prompt on answers including \"Sudan\" before mentioned; accept <b><u>Wad Habuba</u></b> Revolt before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The victor of this battle was paid tribute by Handel's opera <em>Judas Maccabeus</em>. The losing commander of this battle was forced to land on the island of Benbecula after facing a storm during an escape. An attack at Nairn that preceded this battle was planned by George Murray, who attempted to recreate a similar success as at Prestonpans. The nickname \"Butcher\" was given to Prince William, Duke of Cumberland after this battle, which was a defeat for the Stuart royal Bonnie Prince Charlie. For the point, name this decisive battle of the 1745 Jacobite Uprising.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Culloden</u></b> (accept Battle of <b><u>Culloden</u></b> Moor; accept Bl\u00e0r <b><u>Ch\u00f9il Lodair</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Citing the Twelve Tables, this thinker openly criticized the use of usury in commerce in his only surviving treatise, <em>De Agri Cultura</em>. With Manius Acilius [[ah-KIL-ee-us]] Glabrio, this man defeated a combined Aetolian League and Seleucid army under Antiochus the Great at the 191 BC Battle of Thermopylae. This writer of the Italian historiography <em>Origins</em> had a \"Younger\" relative of the same name who opposed the rise of Caesar. The phrase \"Carthago delenda est\" ended all the speeches of, for the point, what Roman orator who encouraged the Third Punic War?", "answer": "<b><u>Cato</u></b> (accept <b><u>Cato</u></b> the Elder; or <b><u>Cato</u></b> the Censor; do not accept \"Cato the Younger\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s capture was believed to have been orchestrated by John Stokesley. The last words of this man were, \u201cLord! Open the king of England\u2019s eyes.\u201d Henry VIII [[the Eighth]] used this man\u2019s <em>The Obedience of a Christian Man</em> to rationalize separating the Church of England from papal authority. The king then wanted this man to be extradited after he opposed the monarch\u2019s annulment to Catherine of Aragon in his <em>The Practice of</em> <em>Prelates</em>. Executed for heresy in 1536, for the point, which scholar translated the Bible from the original Hebrew and Greek into Early Modern English?", "answer": "William <b><u>Tyndale</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tyndale</u></b> Bible)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Dinosaur bones were fashioned into chandeliers for this state's Zolochiv Castle, built by John III as a gift for his French wife, Marie of Arquen [[are-KEN]]. It's not Russia, but Jewish people in fixed income occupations known as <em>Arendator</em> were attacked in this state during the Khmelnytsky Uprising. This state lost one-third of its population during the Swedish Deluge, and this union formed after Duke Jogaila [[yah-GEH-wah]] married Queen Jadwiga [[yahd-WEE-gah]]. The cities of Krakow and Warsaw served as the capital of, for the point, what early modern state which experienced three partitions?", "answer": "<b><u>Poland-Lithuania</u></b> (prompt on partial answers; accept <b><u>Polish-Lithuania</u></b>n Commonwealth; accept the Kingdom of <b><u>Poland</u></b> and the Grand Duchy of <b><u>Lithuania</u></b>; accept Rzeczpospolita <b><u>Obojga Narod\u00f3w</u></b>; accept <b><u>Abiej\u0173 Taut\u0173</u></b> Respublika; prompt on  \"Commonwealth\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The Khartoum Resolution was passed following this conflict, with one league putting forth the \"Three No's\" which refused to trade, recognize, or declare peace with an adversarial neighbor. The three-year long War of Attrition followed this war's swift conclusion, with Gamal Abdel Nasser supporting low-intensity warfare in the occupied Sinai Peninsula. The long-lasting occupation of the West Bank and the Gaza Strip occurred after, for the point, what short-lived war between Israel and its Arab neighbors in the 1960s?", "answer": "<b><u>Six-Day</u></b> War (accept Milhemet <b><u>Sheshet Ha Yamim</u></b>; or an-<b><u>Naksah</u></b>; accept <b><u>June</u> </b>War before mentioned; accept <b><u>Third Arab\u2013Israeli</u></b> War before \"For the point\")", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A leader in this country appointed a poet from a neighboring country named Froyl\u00e1n Turcios [[froy-LAHN toor-SEE-ohss]] to serve as his secretary. An attack on the Bonanza mine in this country was overseen by a man who, while visiting Mexico, established close ties with the Salvadoran revolutionary Farabundo Marti. Jose Maria Moncada and Adolfo Diaz served as leaders of this country, the latter of whom granted the U.S. rights to build a canal through its namesake lake. For the point, guerillas loyal to Augusto Sandinho, the Sandinistas, operated in what Central American country southeast of Honduras?", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Nicaragua</u></b> (accept Republica de <b><u>Nicaragua</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s first act as emperor was to annex the Nabataean Kingdom to create the province of Arabia Petraea. During this man\u2019s reign, the <em>alimenta</em>, a welfare program that helped orphans and poor children, was formed and funded by putting mortgages on farms throughout Italy. This man sacked Ctesiphon, capital of the Parthian Empire, and commemorated his victory against the Dacians [[DAY-shuns]] in a namesake \"Column.\" For the point, name this second of the Five Good Emperors, declared the \u201cbest ruler\u201d by the Roman Senate.", "answer": "<b><u>Trajan</u></b> (or Caesar Nerva <b><u>Traian</u></b>us; accept <b><u>Trajan</u></b>'s Column)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In an act of war protest, this man once set his boat, the <em>Tigris</em>, on fire off the coast of Djibouti while on a nine-nation expedition to determine how Egyptians and Mesopotamians could have contacted the Indus Valley Civilization. One book by this man describes another expedition that sailed from Morocco to Barbados and was named after the Egyptian deity Ra. For the point, name this Norwegian adventurer and experimental archeologist whose travels across the Pacific in a balsa wood raft are chronicled in the book <em>Kon-Tiki</em>.", "answer": "Thor <b><u>Heyerdahl</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Henry Dodge gained national recognition in the U.S. for his conduct during this war, overall U.S. command of which was given to Henry Atkinson. The Battle of Kellogg's Grove during this war included Abraham Lincoln's only personal combat experience. This conflict opened with Isaiah Stillman's flight after he and his Illinois militia were attacked by the British Band. The Battles of Wisconsin Heights and Bad Axe concluded, for the point, what 1832 frontier conflict against a namesake Sauk warrior?", "answer": "<b><u>Black Hawk</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Nazi operation named for this officer ordered the Wehrmacht [[VEHR-mahkt]] to defend Berlin to the last man. This man, who may have coined the term \"Armchair General,\" assisted in organizing the Convention of Tauroggen, which created an anti-Napoleonic coalition in 1812. This man described the uncertainty of ongoing battles as the \"Fog of War,\" and he said, \"War was the Continuation of Politics by another means.\" For the point, name this 19th century German military theorist who wrote <em>On War</em>.", "answer": "Karl von <b><u>Clausewitz</u></b> (or Carl Philipp Gottfried (or Gottlieb) von <b><u>Clausewitz</u></b>; accept Operation <b><u>Clausewitz</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person once confronted the local managers of Johnson Controls with the \u201cDownsizer of the Year Award\u201d and an 80 cent check for \u201cthe first hour\u2019s wage for a Mexican worker.\u201d This person enraged Ray Bradbury after he parodied a Bradbury novel's title in one of his films. This person said, \u201cShame on you, Mr. Bush!\u201d after winning an Oscar for <em>Bowling for Columbine</em>. For the point, what controversial American filmmaker created documentaries such as <em>The Big One</em> and <em>Fahrenheit 9/11</em>?", "answer": "Michael <b><u>Moore</u></b> (or Michael Francis <b><u>Moore</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Thanks to this man\u2019s connection with Maximilian I, he was given possession of the County of Kirchberg. After extracting metals from Bohemia and Hungary, this man and his family had a monopolistic hold on copper in Europe. This man funded Charles V's election as Holy Roman Emperor and built a namesake chapel in St. Anne's Church, as well as the oldest social housing project in the world. For the point, name this German banker and merchant, considered the richest man in early modern Europe.", "answer": "Jakob <b><u>Fugger</u></b> of the Lily (accept Jakob <b><u>Fugger</u></b> the Rich; or <b><u>Jakob II</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Gideon Gono was the longtime head of one institution in this country that introduced the RTG in 2019. Tracts known as \u201cCommunal Areas\u201d were claimed for resettlement purposes as part of a mass land redistribution campaign in this country during the 2000s. An image of a sign reading \u201cStarving Billionaire\u201d was used by media outlets to bring attention to hyperinflation in this country whose longtime ruler was in power from 1987 to 2017. Former vice president Emmerson Mnangagwa [[mm-nahn-GAH-gwah]] has governed this country since 2017. For the point, name this African country once led by Robert Mugabe.", "answer": "Republic of <b><u>Zimbabwe</u></b> (or Nyika ye<b><u>Zimbabwe</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This politician once poked fun at his nickname by saying, \u201cEggheads of the world unite, you have nothing to lose but your yolks!\u201d William M. Gallagher won the 1953 Pulitzer Prize for capturing a photo of a hole under this politician\u2019s right shoe. As the U.S. Ambassador to the United Nations, this politician admitted he was \u201chumiliated\u201d when he did not know the full extent of the Bay of Pigs invasion. A governor of Illinois, for the point, what politician lost to Dwight D. Eisenhower during the 1952 and 1956 presidential elections?", "answer": "Adlai E. <b><u>Stevenson</u></b> II (or Adlai Ewing <b><u>Stevenson</u></b> II)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In 1970, this woman's remains were purported to have been discovered by the KGB who then haphazardly exhumed, cremated, and tossed them into a tributary of the Elbe River. This woman, who served as assistant to Official Party Photographer Heinrich Hoffman, supposedly overrode armament minister Albert Speer's call for a ban on women's luxury goods in 1943. The only time this woman appeared in official press photographs was during the 1936 Berlin Olympics. For the point, name this mistress-turned-wife of Adolf Hitler, whose life ended alongside him in the Fuhrerbunker.", "answer": "Eva <b><u>Braun</u></b> (or Eva Anna Paula <b><u>Braun</u></b>; accept <b><u>E</u></b>va Anna Paula <b><u>Hitler</u></b>; prompt on \"Hitler\" or \"Hitler's wife\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This civilization created a fresco with five dolphins in the Queen\u2019s Megaron. This civilization\u2019s Phaistos Disc is an early example of typographic print and is inscribed with symbols similar to this civilization\u2019s undeciphered language, Linear A. An eruption on Thera made this civilization vulnerable to the Mycenaeans, who succeeded them as the dominant civilization on Crete. For the point, name this early Greek civilization whose namesake king built the Labyrinth.", "answer": "<b><u>Minoan</u></b> Civilization (accept <b><u>Minoan</u></b>s; prompt on \"Minos\")", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "John Bartle\u2019s experiences in this war are the subject of a novel by Kevin Powers. <em>Granta</em> magazine published the title story in a set of twelve placed during this war that includes \u201cAfter Action Report\u201d and \u201cTen Kliks South.\u201d Stephen King\u2019s 2021 novel <em>Billy</em> <em>Summers</em> focuses on a veteran of this war who becomes a hitman. Phil Klay\u2019s collection <em>Redeployment</em> is set during this war and was partly inspired by the author\u2019s experiences in Anbar Province. For the point, name this war often featured in American literature that began with a 2003 invasion.", "answer": "<b><u>Iraq</u></b> War (accept Operation <b><u>Iraq</u></b>i Freedom; accept Operation <b><u>New Dawn</u></b>; prompt on \u201cWar or Terror\u201d)", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "Before this event, Olympic gold-medalist Terry McDermott posed for a photo pretending to cut the hair of one of the performers. A caption read \u201cSORRY GIRLS, HE\u2019S MARRIED\u201d when introducing one performer during this event. The music video for the Outkast song \u201cHey Ya!\u201d was inspired by this landmark televised event. Sparking the start of the \u201cBritish Invasion,\u201d for the point, what 1964 event televised the debut of a Liverpool band to American audiences?", "answer": "The <b><u>Beatles</u></b> 1964 U.S. debut on <em>The Ed</em> <em><b><u>Sullivan</u></b> Show</em> (accept any equivalents to \u201cdebut of the <b><u>Beatles</u></b> on <em>The Ed</em> <em><b><u>Sullivan</u></b> Show</em>\u201d; prompt on \u201cdebut of the Beatles\u201d; prompt on \u201cBeatles performance\u201d)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A claimant to this position from the House of Aberffraw died while attempting to escape the Tower of London after falling from a knotted rope. A man with this title signed the Treaty of Worcester with the newly crowned Henry III to protect his conquests of Southern Powys [[POW-us]]. The last native ruler to hold this title, Llywelyn [[loo-EL-len]], died while fighting the English during the Battle of Orewin Bridge. For the point, name this title now held by Charles of Edinburgh, traditionally held by the heir apparent to the British throne.", "answer": "<b><u>Prince of Wales</u></b> (accept <b><u>Tywysog Cymru</u></b>; do not accept \"King of Wales\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Eastern Airlines Flight 401 crashed in this region after its crew became distracted by a burnt-out landing gear indicator light. In this region, Hamilton Disston purchased over four million acres of land near St. Cloud to build canals. One book about this region is subtitled <em>River of Grass</em> and was written by Marjory Stoneman Douglass. This region's drainage was accelerated under the administration of Governor Napoleon Bonaparte Broward. Home to the assimilated Seminole people, for the point, what is this large region of marshy wetlands in South Florida?", "answer": "The <b><u>Everglades</u></b> (accept <b><u>Everglades</u></b> National Park)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In a text called <em>On the Sacred Disease</em>, Hippocrates attributes this figure with causing a form of epilepsy that mimics the state of a horse. Alexander the Great prayed for this deity to cast a four-horse chariot before heading to the Battle of Issus. This god\u2019s temple in the city of Mantinea was restored by Hadrian while another temple on Cape Sounion was strategically placed in view of all incoming and exiting ships. For the point, who is the Greek god of horses, storms, and the sea?", "answer": "<b><u>Poseidon</u></b> (do not accept or prompt on \"Neptune\")", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "One caricature about these events depicts a footrace, with one man saying, \u201cHow can I get over the rail fence?\u201d while his opponent remarks, \u201cIt can\u2019t stop me for I built it.\u201d One participant of these events suggested the Freeport Doctrine in place of the Lecompton Constitution. The incumbent participant in this event won an election after receiving the public support of John J. Crittenden. For the point, what series of highly-publicized debates were conducted between two candidates for a United States Senate seat in Illinois?", "answer": "<b><u>Lincoln-Douglas</u></b> Debates (accept the Great <b><u>Debates</u></b> of <b><u>1858</u></b>; accept descriptive answers involving debates between Abraham <b><u>Lincoln</u></b> and Stephen A. <b><u>Douglas</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "French astronomer Jacques du Chevreul [[doo-shev-RUHL]] rejected this man\u2019s claim that Mars was located under the sun, as that would mean the heavens were permeable. This astronomer wrote the poem <em>Elegy to Dania</em> after being exiled by Christian IV. Johannes Kepler used observational data collected by this astronomer in the <em>Rudolphine</em> <em>Tables</em>. Known for his metallic nose, for the point, what Danish astronomer is also known for his accurate and comprehensive observations made without the use of a telescope?", "answer": "Tycho <b><u>Brahe</u></b> (or Tyge Ottesen <b><u>Brahe</u></b>)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "This company\u2019s first test vehicle was called the Charon [[\"Sharon\"]]. This company announced a plan to \u201cprovide anyone with the opportunity to establish their own address in orbit\u201d in a project called Orbital Reef. One person aboard one of this company's vehicles was 82-year-old Wally Funk, who was the oldest person to go to space until that record was broken by William Shatner nearly three months later. The New Shepard is operated by, for the point, what aerospace company that was founded by Jeff Bezos?", "answer": "<b><u>Blue Origin</u></b>, LLC", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "During a 2 A.M. phone call, a majority whip from this state told Bill Clinton, \u201cHow could I ever look in the faces of our children and grandchildren had I not voted for Barack Obama?\u201d A senator from this state holds the record for the longest filibuster, speaking against the Civil Rights Act of 1957 for over 24 hours. Currently represented by Jim Clyburn, for the point, which state was also represented by politicians like Strom Thurmond and John C. Calhoun?", "answer": "<b><u>South Carolina</u></b> (or <b><u>SC</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person was the first president of an organization called the Ninety-Nines. A 2018 discovery of bones found on the island of Nikumaroro were believed to be this person\u2019s remains. One theory surrounding the whereabouts of this person and their companion, Fred Noonan, was that they were executed by Japanese soldiers on Saipan. For the point, what American pilot disappeared while attempting to be the first woman to complete a circumnavigational airplane flight?", "answer": "Amelia <b><u>Earhart</u></b> (or Amelia Mary <b><u>Earhart</u></b>)  <b>Extra Questions </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This kingdom's independence was secured when 2,000 volunteers supported by Fyodor Radetsky's soldiers turned back 40,000 Ottoman soldiers at the Battle of Shipka Pass. The oppressive taxes of a tsar named Peter from this kingdom prompted Bogomil to found a namesake heretical sect of Orthodox Christianity. This empire's tsar Kaloyan defeated the Latin Empire at the Battle of Adrianople. Basil II of the Byzantine Empire earned a nickname for \"slaying\" this empire's subjects. For the point, name this Balkan empire which had capitals at Tarnovo and Sofia.", "answer": "<b><u>Bulgaria</u></b>n Empire (or <b><u>Balgar</u></b>sko tsarstvo; accept <b><u>Bulgar</u></b>s; accept Basil the <b><u>Bulgar</u></b> Slayer)", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}